Madam, your daughter should sit.
女士 您女儿应该站站好
Stand up straight.
立正站直
This is Master Cromwell.
这位是克伦威尔学士
He used to be a money-lender. Now he writes all the laws.
他以前是个放债者 现在负责撰写所有的法律章程
I have heard all about your new bill
我听说你的新议案
inducing the King to describe himself as the head of the church?
诱使国王将自己视为英格兰教区的首脑？
The Pope is the head of the church everywhere.
只有教皇冕下一人是全世界教区的最高首脑
The lawfulness of all government flows from the...
所有政权的合法性都是经过...
..from...
经过...
Will you not sit down, Princess Mary?
坐下来吧 玛丽公主殿下
It's just the heat.
这椅子不会凉着您
I beg your madam to consider it in this way -
我请求王后您换一下思路
the King has merely defined a position which ancient precedents...
国王陛下只不过是重新定义了一个职位的概念 何况古有先例...
Ancient precedents?
自古而有的先例？
Precedents that you've invented these last three months.
那不过是你这三个月里编出来的先例而已
As for "induced" - Your Highness knows the King cannot be led.
至于您说"诱使" 王后您是知道的国王陛下是不会轻易被引导的
But he can be enticed.
但能被怂恿诱惑
He has ridden off without saying goodbye.
他连一句再见都没有说 抛弃一切离开了
He's never done that before. Never.
他以前从未这样做过 从未有之！
Well, I think he means to hunt out of Chertsey for a few days.
这个 我想他是去切特西那边狩猎几天而已
With the woman. The person.
是和那个女人一起去
Your Highness will be going to another palace.
国王陛下去了另外的行宫
He has chosen the More, in Hertfordshire,
他挑了在赫特福德郡的莫尔家
which as you know is very comfortable.
您也知道 那里气候宜人
It was one of your cardinal's houses, wasn't it?
那曾经是你们某个红衣主教的宫殿吧
So it's bound to be lavish.
所以必定是奢华至极的
I expected this.
希望如此
But I didn't expect he would send a man like you to tell me.
但我不希望他随便派个你这样的人来告诉我
I want to give you something.
我想给你样东西
A present.
当作礼物
Name anything you want.
任何你想要的东西
What is it?
你想要什么
This bill of yours.
你的那项法案
It's not my bill.
这不是我的法案
Taking power from the bishops, making Henry head of the church.
从主教们身上夺取权力 再赋予亨利为教会首脑
Aren't you afraid?
你难道不害怕么
Of what?
害怕什么
There's this girl called Elizabeth Barton making prophecies.
有一个叫伊丽莎白 巴顿的女孩做出来预言
They're calling her the Holy Maid.
他们管她叫 圣女
She's saying Henry won't reign for a year if he marries Anne.
她说如若亨利娶了安妮 他的王位终将不保
And there's a new star by the moon, and the...
还有说月亮旁边新冒出来了一个星星
It's not a star. It's a comet.
那不是星星 那是彗星
..and the last time it appeared was under King John
上次它出现还是在约翰国王在位时
and the cattle stopped breeding and the grass stopped growing
那时万物凋零 寸草不生
and the birds fell from the sky.
千山鸟飞绝
Well, I'm sure if that happens, we can reverse our policy.
如果真的发生这些事 我们倒是可以调整政策的方向性了
I don't believe in omens.
我一点也不信预兆这回事
They've arrested a barrister - James Bainham.
他们逮捕了一个律师 詹姆斯 班罕
You know him, don't you?
你认识他的吧？
Yes. He's a good man.
对 他是个好人
He was handing out the gospel in English.
但他被搜出了英译版的圣经
What if they torture Bainham?
如果他们严刑逼供怎么办
What if he...gives names?
如果他供出了你怎么办
What's that to me? Thomas More already knows my name.
不用担心我 托马斯 莫尔早就知道了
Those for the bill to my right, those against to my left.
同意法案的请站我右手边 反对的站左手边
I think the "ayes" have it. The "ayes" have it!
我想 法案通过了！ 通过！
Your Majesty.
国王陛下
Congratulations. I take it the division of the house was your idea?
恭喜你了 我猜这分队投票是你的主意吧
I thought this way His Majesty could see who was with him
我想这样才能让国王陛下一目了然他的追随者
and who against him.
及反对者们
In the Commons, at least.
至少也要分清国会中的派别
I know Stephen is opposed to the bill, Cromwell.
我知道斯蒂芬是反对法案的 克伦威尔
I don't want a servant who will agree with everything.
我也不想有个只会应声附和的仆从
I need men who aren't afraid of controversy.
我需要的是能应付论战的人才
Now, I know you two quarrel.
我知道你们俩一直争论不休
You must learn to pull together.
但现在 你们必须要学会通力合作
This winter, you have to be yoked to the plough.
这个寒冬 你们俩 轭不离犁 犁不离轭 一起干活
You won't find it so easy passing your bill through the House of Lords.
你应该知道让上议院通过法案并不是件易事
Thomas More and the old aristocracy are for the Pope
托马斯 莫尔和古老的家族们都是支持教皇的
and not afraid to say so.
且并不怕国王知晓
Well, we'll see. Archbishop Warham.
这个嘛 等着看好了 沃罕大主教
This um, prophetess you harbour in your diocese - Eliza Barton?
那位被你藏在教区里的女先知 伊丽莎白 巴顿
How is she getting on?
她还好吗
What do you want, Cromwell?
你想要干嘛 克伦威尔
Well, I hear that she's telling people
我听说她四处传播
that if the King marries Lady Anne, he has only a year to reign.
如国王娶了安妮夫人 那就不久于王位了
I just wondered who is controlling her.
我只想知道谁教她这么说的
She may be a simple country girl but she has a genuine gift.
她也许只是一个简单的乡村姑娘 但她确实天赋异禀
She does, doesn't she?
是啊 确实是
I hear she can tell you where your dead relatives are.
我想她也能预知您是因何而亡的
If it's in Heaven, she speaks with a higher voice,
如在天堂 她将更高亢
if in Hell, with a deep voice.
如在地狱 她将更低沉
She can also tell what sins
她也可以一见面
weigh upon a man as soon as she meets him.
就说出这人的罪行
What would she make of you?
她见到你 会说什么呢
How was Antwerp?
安特卫普之行怎么样 [比利时城市]
Glad to be home.
很高兴到家了
Oh.
噢
For show. In case I got stopped.
装装样子的 怕沿途出乱子
Hmm.
嗯
- Mm-hmm.  - Centre seam.
- 嗯哼     - 在中间的夹缝里
- What does he say?   - You carried it without reading it?
- 他说什么?           - 你一直带着却没有读吗
I didn't want to know. In case.
为了以防不测 我不想提前知道
If Thomas More came anywhere near you,
如果托马斯 莫尔 想方设法要接近你的话
I'd drag him out of his court in Westminster
我会将他拖出他的威斯敏斯特教区
and beat his head on the cobbles until I'd knocked some of God's love into it.
然后用鹅卵石上砸他的脑袋 直到把上帝怜爱砸进去
- Will Tynedale come back?  - M'hm.
- 汀代尔会回来吗            - 嗯
When the King says yes to the scripture being translated into English.
只要国王同意将圣经译成英文
But even then, he won't trust More to give him safe conduct, because
但即使那样 他也不会相信莫尔给他安全保证 因为
More says you don't have to keep the promise you made to a heretic.
莫尔曾说 根本不必对一个异教徒的信守承诺
Anyway, Tynedale still refuses to support the King's divorce.
总之 汀代尔仍在严词抗争国王的离婚案
You'd think he'd bend a point of principle to make
你也许会想 他作为英格兰国王的朋友
a friend of the King of England.
不应该那么坚持原则的
But, no. Tynedale and More - they deserve each other.
但其实不然 汀代尔和莫尔 他们俩还真是配
These mules who pose as men.
俩杂种都装的像正人君子一样
My lady.
夫人
It's the bow.
弓有问题
No doubt. It could be the brace height.
当然 应该是支架的高度
Could we swap the bows, please?
可以帮我们换下弓吗
She was the same in the nursery.
她还是和小时候一样
Where's Robin Hood? I have dispatches.
"罗宾汉"在哪  我已将派人找他去了
He won't look at them until sundown.
他到日落时 才会见他们
Won't he be occupied then?
他之后就不忙了吗
She's selling herself by the inch.
她在一点一点诱惑他
She wants a cash present for every advance above her knee.
她每露出一截大腿 就要很多现金礼物
She's got long legs.
并且她的腿很长
By the time he reaches her secret part, the nation'll be bankrupt!
等国王能一捣黄龙时 国家估计也破产了
I er, I had heard a rumour...
我...我听到了一个谣言...
She isn't. I would know.
她没怀 否则我会知道的
If she thickened at all, I'd be the one to have to let out her clothes.
如果她把衣服加厚了 我也是要帮她垫衣服的人
I know her waist by the inch.
我知道她腰围的每分每寸
Besides, she can't be. Because they still haven't.
而且 她不可能怀的 因为他们还没有...
- She'd tell you?    - Of course.
- 她会告诉你这些     - 当然
Out of spite.
一气之下说的
I want a job.
我想要一份工作
An official post.
正式的职位
In the Jewel House, perhaps?
在珠宝宫殿最好
I'll tell her.
我会告诉她的
She made Tom Wyatt a poet and Harry Percy mad.
她让汤姆 怀特成了一名诗人 哈利 珀西为之疯狂
I'm sure she has some idea what to make you.
我肯定她对你也有些想法
Last week, at Greenwich,
上周 在格林威治
a Friar preached to us
一个修士给我们传道
about the good king who was corrupted by the wicked Jezebel.
讲的是关于一个好国王被一个淫妇所毁的故事
Apparently she built a pagan temple
她建了一座异教徒的寺宇
and let the priests of Baal into the palace.
并且让巴尔的信徒进入礼拜  [堕落神 耶和华最大的敌人]
She ended up being thrown out of a window.
最后她被扔出了窗外
I'm the Jezebel, you see
现在我成了那个淫妇了 你懂没
and you're the priests of Baal.
而你就是信仰巴尔的教徒
I see.
我明白
More has arrested a barrister, James Bainham.
莫尔逮捕了一名律师 詹姆斯 班罕
- What do you expect me to do about it?   - Talk to the King.
- 你想让我做什么                          - 和国王求求情
You know how to please him, I suppose?
你知道该如何取悦他的
My maidenhead for your lawyer?
用我的处女之身换你的律师
He'll be released.
我保证他会被释放的
Well...
嗯...
..Little Bilney wasn't.
..小比尔耐就没有释放
They burnt him in Norwich.
他们在诺威奇把他活活烧死了
Your barrister friend will recant and he'll be released.
只要你的律师朋友公开道歉认错 他就马上被释放
And if he doesn't?
如果他不呢
Then he's a fool.
那他就是个傻瓜
People should say whatever will keep them alive.
人不为己 天诛地灭
You would, wouldn't you?
难道你不是吗
What's that?
你抱的什么
Ah.
啊
It's a gift for one of your women.
给一个小女孩的礼物
The little girl who always cries.
就是那个经常哭的小女孩
What?
怎么了
Didn't you hear?
你难道没听说吗
No, what?
没有 什么事
Her father - dear old Sir John Seymour?
她的父亲 亲爱的老约翰 西摩爵士
He was caught in the hayloft with his son Edward's wife.
在干草棚里 他和他儿子爱德华的妻子 被捉奸了
It seems he's had her every week for the last two years.
好像前两年里 他每周都能和她鬼混
Edward's put the wife into a nunnery
然后爱德华就把他妻子打发进了尼姑庵去
and I don't think we'll see dear old Sir John at court soon.
所以我可不认为我们能很快在议会上看到亲爱的老约翰爵士了
And the daughter? Jane, is it?
那他女儿 叫珍妮的 对吧
Pasty-face? Gone to Wiltshire.
那个脸色苍白的女孩吗 去了威尔特郡
It's her best bet to get into a nunnery too.
其实她最好的选择也是去尼姑庵
No-one want will want to marry the milksop now.
现在没有人想娶这种懦弱的人
What is it?
这是什么东西
It's only...
这只是...
..a book of needlework patterns.
...一本有着编织图案的书
You don't LIKE her...do you?
你是喜欢她吗
Because I'm not sure it's proper for you to send her a present.
因为我不能确定 你送她礼物这事是否合适
Well, it's not like it's tales from Boccaccio.
哎呀 这又不是什么薄伽丘的童话集
Oh, they could tell Boccaccio a tale!
噢 他们居然称薄伽丘那鬼东西叫童话!
Those sinners at Wolf Hall.
那些身在狼厅的罪人们
Mm-hmm?
嗯哼?
Lord Chancellor.
大法官阁下
You should have warned me.
你应该先知会我一声的
You'll have something to eat?
您要吃些东西吗
- Thank you, no.  - Something to drink then? Some wine?
- 谢谢 不了       - 那要喝点什么 来点酒?
Your friend, Bainham?
你的朋友 班罕
He has recanted his heresy
他已经抛弃了那些异端邪说
and been set free.
被释放了
I thought you should know.
我觉得你应该先知晓
Well, thank you.
是啊 谢谢你
I heard that he'd been put to the rack.
我却听说 他被用刑了
To save his soul, I would have had him whipped,
为了拯救他的灵魂 我是主张对他用鞭刑的
I'd have had him burnt with irons,
我主张将他绑着手腕吊起来与钢铁一同燃烧
I'd have had him...hung by his wrists.
与钢铁...一同燃烧
In these last ten years, the Turks have taken Belgrade.
在过去十年中 土耳其人已经占领了贝尔格莱德
They have lit their campfires in the great library at Buda.
他们已经将营火烧到了布达的大图书馆
It is only two years since they were at the gates of Vienna.
这距离他们被困在维也纳 不过只有两年而已
Why would you want to make another breach in the walls of Christendom?
你为什么还要在基督世界中 再搞一次大破坏呢
The King of England is not an infidel.
英格兰国王 并不是异教徒
- Nor am I.   - Aren't you?
- 我也不是    - 你不是吗
I think your faith is for purchase.
我认为你的信仰是利益至上
I think you would serve the Sultan if the price was right.
只要出价满意 你甚至都会去效忠苏丹[奥斯曼帝国的最高统治者]
You think because you're a councillor you can negotiate
不要以为你现在是个小小议员 你就可以背着国王
with heretics behind the King's back. You're wrong.
跟那些异教徒打交道 你错了
I know about your letters that come and go.
我已经知道你那些往来的信件了
I know you are in communication with Tyndale.
也知道你一直在和汀代尔保持联系
Are you threatening me?
你是在威胁我吗
I'm just interested.
只是感兴趣而已
Yes. Yes.
是 是的
That's precisely what I'm doing.
这是我一直在做的事
You still haven't told me what you want as a present.
你还是没告诉我你想要什么礼物
My mother knows.
我妈妈知道了
About us.
我们的事
I...I think...
我...我想...
I think we've done what we have
我想我们已经做了我们该做的事
because when Liz died, we were shocked.
因为莉兹去世的时候 我们都很震惊
We were sorry.
我们很遗憾
I think we have to leave off that now.
但我认为我们现在都该放下了
If...if my husband had -
如果...如果我丈夫...
God forgive me but every winter I think is his last -
上帝宽恕我 但每到冬天我都觉得会是他的最后一段生命
then of course, I would, without question.
然后 当然...我想和你... 毫无疑问
But then...
但是...
the law wouldn't allow that, so...
法律不会允许这样的 所以...
If, if you want to marry, Mercy has her list.
如果你想要续娶 梅茜有给你准备一长串名单
You probably have your own list, with names on it we don't know, so...
你也可能有了心仪的人选 也许还是我们不认识的人 所以...
Liz.
莉兹
Johane.
约翰娜
Francis Bryan is here. It's something bad.
佛朗西斯 布莱恩来了 有些不好的事发生了
He's Anne's cousin. I'll have to...
他是安妮的表亲 我一定要...
What does Percy's wife say?
珀西的妻子怎么说
She says she's going to petition Parliament for divorce.
她说她会去请求国会准许离婚
She says he hasn't shared her bed for two years,
她说她已经有两年是自己独睡的了
and when she asked him why he said he couldn't.
而且她问他原因时 他说他不能
Why has she waited two years to ask?
那为什么她要等了两年之后才问
She has been asking.
她一直在问
And last night, he finally admitted he can't sleep with her
昨晚 他终于承认了他做不到
- because they're not really married.  - What?
- 因为他们没有真正结婚                 - 什么?
Because Harry Percy's actually married to Anne Boleyn.
因为哈利 珀西实际上是与安妮 博林结了婚的
Bring them down!
把它们弄下来!
We've swept up most of the broken glass.
我们已经把大部分碎玻璃渣扫干净了
Shut the door, Francis and don't let anybody in.
关上门 佛朗西斯 别让任何人进来
I suggest we pack Anne's bags and send her to Kent.
我建议我们把安妮的东西打包 然后送她去肯特
The King's anger once...
国王的怒气一度...
Say one more word and I'll punch you.
再说一个字 我就揍你
The King has said there must be an inquiry, before the whole council.
国王已经说了必须当着整个议会的面 进行一场审问
If Anne has concealed a secret marriage...
如果安妮真的隐瞒了一桩秘密婚姻...
Jesus, I wish I could divorce you!
天啊 你闭嘴我真希望我能跟你离婚!
I wish you'd had a pre-contract. But no chance of that.
我真希望你有个婚前契约 但没这机会了
The fields were black with men running the other fucking way!
在这么下去 这里所有人全完了!
- George!  - I deny everything.
- 乔治!    - 我否认一切
- Good.   - Harry Percy spoke of love, I'll allow that.
- 很好    - 哈利 珀西 是说过爱我 我也认同了他的爱情
But there was no contract.
可我们之间根本就没有任何婚姻契约
And no consummation.
也没有行房之事
My sister is a notorious virgin.
我妹妹是个名声不好的处女
How was the King when you spoke to him?
你跟国王说这事的时候 他态度如何
What is the use of calling in Master Cromwell and not telling him what has already occurred?
如果不告诉克伦威尔大人事实真相  那叫他到这里来干什么
The King walked out of the room and left her standing.
国王拂袖而去 留她独自站在那
It seems to me there are a number of approaches here.
在我看来 这事有很多解决办法
Oh, Jesus Christ!
噢 天哪!
By the thrice-beshitten shroud of Lazarus!
[我实在是不会翻了 有大神 请指点！]
While you're selecting your approach, your daughter, sir,
你还在慢慢选你的办法时 你的女儿
- is being slandered.  - Harry...  - The King's mind is poisoned,
在被人造谣中伤         - 哈利...   - 国王的思想已经被毒害
and this family's fortune is unmaking before your fucking eyes!
而这个家族的财富 也会在你眼前灰飞烟灭!
Will you let me speak?
能让我说句话么
Harry Percy was persuaded once to forget his claim.
哈利 佩西曾被强制去忘记他的誓词
- If he was fixed once...    - Yes. But the Cardinal fixed him then.
-如果他能再被强制一次...     - 的确如此 不过那时有红衣主教能压制他
And unfortunately the Cardinal is dead.
但很不幸 红衣主教现在死了
Lady Anne,
安妮夫人
if the Pope cannot stop you becoming Queen -
如果连教皇冕下都不能阻止您登上王后宝座
and I don't think he can -
当然 我也不认为他具备这样的能力
I don't see why Harry Percy should be allowed to stand in your way.
那么 哈利 珀西就更没能力能阻拦您了
So shift him out of it.
所以就直接把他赶回去呗
Do it.
做去吧
Beat his fucking skull in.
真他妈想打爆他脑袋
Why don't you come up?!
上来玩玩啦
Looking for a woman?
要找女人玩玩吗
Oh, God, yes, I thought you'd come.
呵 我就猜到你会来了
Hey  out.
嘿 出去
Well, you're wasting your time. I was pledged to Anne.
你现在就是在浪费时间 安妮对我做过保证
She allowed me such freedom with herself
我能陪她享受这闲暇时光
as only a betrothed woman would allow.
做一个订婚的女人该做的事
The Cardinal bullied me out of saying anything last time,
那次红衣主教恐吓我 不许说任何事
but I'm not afraid to speak the truth now.
现在我也不怕说出真相了
My lord, you've said what you have to say.
阁下 你已经说了你该说的话了
Now listen to me.
现在 该轮到我说了
You're a man whose money is almost spent.
你是个一穷二白的人
I'm a man who knows how you've spent it.
我也对你了如指掌
You're a man who has borrowed all over Europe.
你在全欧洲都已经是债台高筑了
I'm a man who knows your creditors.
我也恰好知道你所有的欠债人姓甚名谁
One word from me, and all your debts will be called in.
只要我一句话 欠债条能瞬间把你淹没
What are they going to do? Bankers don't have armies.
他们能做什么呢 银行家可没有军队
Neither will you, without any money.
分文没有的你 又拿什么保护自己
My lord, you hold your earldom from the King.
阁下 国王赐予你伯爵爵位
Your task is to secure the north, to defend us against Scotland.
是想让你为他守护北部边防 帮他抵御苏格兰的侵略
If you cannot ensure these things, the King will take your land
如果你让他失望的话 国王毫无疑问 会收回你的封地和头衔
and your titles and give them
转而赏给那些
to someone who will do the job that you cannot do.
能力远在你之上的臣子
No, he won't. He respects all ancient titles.
不 他不会的 他很尊重这些自古流传下来的家族头衔
How can I explain this to you...?
我该怎么向你解释呢
The world is not run from where you think it is.
这个世界已经不再是你所认为的那样了
From border fortresses.
从边疆堡垒
Even from Whitehall.
甚至从白宫
The world is run from Antwerp, from Florence, from Lisbon.
从安特卫普 佛罗伦萨 里斯本
From wherever the merchant ships set sail off into the west.
从那些商船们西行的扬帆之地开始 都变了
Not from castle walls, from counting houses.
不再是城堡的高墙，从数量有限的马匹开始
From the pens that scrape out your promissory notes.
从那些刮花本票的钢笔开始
So believe me when I say
请相信我所说的
that my banker friends and I will rip your life apart.
我会和我那些银行的朋友们一起 毁了你的人生
And then, when you are without money and title, yes, I can picture you
然后 当你失去财产和头衔开始  是的  我都可以想象的出
living in a hovel, wearing homespun,
你身处山洞 身着布衣的画面
bringing home a rabbit for the pot.
打回一只野兔 晚餐煮汤喝
Your lawful wife, Anne Boleyn, skinning and jointing that rabbit.
安妮 博林 你的合法妻子 为兔子剥皮 填料
Yes, I wish you all happiness.
就是这样了 希望你幸福快乐
You were never pre-contracted.
你从来都不会有所察觉
Any understanding you think you have, you didn't have it.
只相信自己心里所想 可事实上 事与愿违
And if you think Lady Anne loves you
如果你认为 安妮夫人是真的爱你
you couldn't be more mistaken.
你大错特错了
I've just come from her.
我刚从她那儿过来
She hates you.
她很厌恶你
She despises you.
瞧不起你
She wants you gone.
恨不得你立马消失
So if you say one more word about Lady Anne's "freedom" with you,
所以 如果你再说一句和安妮夫人享受自由的话
I will come and drag you out of whatever hole
你是在自掘坟墓
you are cowering in and the Duke of Norfolk will bite your bollocks off.
而诺尔福克公爵也会把你的臭嘴撕裂
I do hope that's clear, my lord?
阁下 我这么解释 你应该明白了吧
Yes, you can all peer in again.
来 你们随意偷看偷听吧
There he is.
他来了
My uncle and I work for his removal for months without success
在他一连数月无政绩被免职之后 我和叔叔就来到这里工作
and now he resigns.
现在 他却辞职了
Over this bill.
结算了工资
His great protest.
他前途无量
England is just a stage to him.
英格兰对于他 只是一个小舞台
Who should replace him?
谁能会接替他的职位
Put it in the King's mind to appoint Audley.
想办法让国王任命 奥德利
He's a good man. And he understands me, I think.
他人不错 而且我想 他也很懂我的心思
Do you think that someone does?
根本没人了解
Cranmer as Archbishop,
身为大主教的克兰麦
Audley as Lord Chancellor.
身为大法官的奥德利
Soon you'll have friends everywhere.
很快 哪里都有你的人了
And for yourself?
那你自己呢
I thought perhaps Keeper of the Jewel House?
我想 也许是珠宝宫殿的看守员吧
Where's the chain of office? He's supposed to hand it over.
办公室的锁链在哪 他应该是要交接的
In the bag.
在那袋子里
So that's it?
所以就这样吗
More is out?
莫尔就这样走了
Shall we go down?
我们要下去么
You...
你啊...
you can't resist it.
你会承受不住的
- No more can you.  - No.
- 你也一样          - 不会的
What will you do now?
你现在准备去干什么
Write.
写书
Pray.
祷告
My recommendation - write only a little and pray a lot.
我的建议  少写 多祈祷
Now, is that a threat?
这算是威胁吗
My turn, don't you think?
也该轮到我了 是吧
We're off to Calais.
我们要去加来
The King of France had agreed to speak to the Pope
法国国王已经同意 一道谏言教皇
in favour of my new marriage.
支持我的新婚姻
We'll meet there to discuss points of a treaty.
我们要在加来见面 探讨谈判的内容
Last time we met,
上次我们见面时
Wolsey arranged everything.
沃尔西操办了所有事
I thought perhaps you could help organise things this time?
这次我想你来安排
Lean on me, Your Majesty.
靠着我 陛下
We'll take mass at Canterbury.
我们会带着大队人马到坎特伯雷
Let the people see their king.
让人们朝见一下他们的国王
Do you know this woman?
你认识这个女人吗
I used to.
以前认识
She reminds me of someone I knew long ago.
她让我想起了很久以前在安特卫普
In Antwerp.
认识的人
What was her name?
她叫什么名字
Anselma.
安赛姆
You've known passion, Cromwell.
你知道什么是激情吗 克伦威尔
With Anne... I shake.
和安妮...时 我会浑身颤抖
Do you understand?
你明白我的意思？
I shake.
我颤抖了
I've tried other women,
我也试过其他女人
tried them just to try to take the edge off the lust...
想让她们激起我的强烈的欲望...
but I failed with all of them.
但全都失败了
Couldn't do it.
我做不到
Which is proof, don't you think?
你不觉得这恰好是证明吗
Proof of the rightness of my pursuit.
证明我的追求是对的
I hunt only one hind -
我只追逐着一个女人
and she takes me from the path and into the woods...
她引领我由幽径到达丛林深处...
Now, away to our cold beds.
现在 回我们的冷被窝里去吧
Or is that just mine?
还是只是我一个人的冷被窝
There's work to do.
你有的忙活了
I have a new post for you.
我有一项新职位给你
I want you to be my Keeper of the Jewel House.
我要你负责看管我的珍宝宫殿
Your Majesty.
陛下
Why not? Why shouldn't I?
为什么不行 谁说我不可以？
Who says I shouldn't employ the son of an honest blacksmith!
谁说我不可以任用一个忠诚无二的铁匠的儿子
Everything that you are,
你的一切
everything that you have,
你拥有的一切
will come from me.
我都能赐予你
Majesty!
陛下！
This is the Holy Maid. Let me see her.
这是那个圣女 让我见见她
Madam, you have something to say to me?
女士 你有什么想对我说的吗
The heretics you have around you must be put into a great fire.
您应该烧死身边的那些异教分子
If you don't do it, you'll burn yourself.
您如果不这么做 被烧死的会是您自己
What heretics? I keep no heretics about my person.
什么异教分子？ 我的人里面没有异端分子
Here's one. If you marry this one, you won't reign seven months.
她就是 如果您和她结婚 您的王位在七个月之内将不保
Couldn't you at least round it up?
你的谎话就不能编的像样点吗
I see your mother - surrounded by pale fires.
我见到了您的母亲 被幽冥鬼火包围着
- My mother? Where?     - She's mad. She should be whipped!
- 我母亲 在哪？         - 她疯了 应该把她鞭笞至死
She's a very holy person. Her speech is inspired by heaven.
她可是圣女  她说的话只受上帝指引
Lightning will strike you!
你会遭雷劈的
Drag her back to the whorehouse
在我踹死她前
before she feels my boot on her arse!
把她给我拖到妓院去！
Take her away! Take her away!
把她带走！带走！
Mistress?
小姐？
I was a servant of the late Cardinal Wolsey.
我曾是已故的沃尔西主教的仆从
I understand you can converse with the souls of the dead.
我知道你可以和死去的灵魂交流
Wondered if you would search for him for me.
所以想知道您是否可以替我寻到他
I would be happy to make an offering.
您可以随便开价
It would have to be a generous donation.
那可是要给教堂一大笔捐赠的
Well, I'm a wealthy man.
没关系 我很富有
I'd have to talk to Father Bocking.
我得和博金神父商量一下
Father Bocking?
博金神父？
He is the lady's spiritual director.
他是圣女的心灵导师
Ah.
噢
Come again and ask me.
下次再来找我问询吧
Mm-hm.
嗯哼
Come with me.
跟我来
My lord.
大人
Fetch your niece away.
把你侄女带走吧
She has done enough diplomacy.
她已经外交够了
What the...
她在搞什么...
By your leave, Highness.
请原谅 陛下
My lady, we shall dance.
夫人 我们去跳曲舞吧
Master Seymour, your sister Jane...?
西摩大人 你的姐姐珍妮...
Odd little creature, isn't she?
脾气很古怪对吧
How... old would she be?
她多大了
I don't know. 20 or so?
不知道 二十岁左右？
She keeps walking around Wolf Hall saying
她一直在狼厅周围四处走动
these are Thomas Cromwell's sleeves.
还说这些都是托马斯 克伦威尔的爪牙
No-one knows what she's talking about.
没人知道她在说什么
Has your father made her a match?
你父亲难道没为她做媒么？
There was some talk of...
有一些议论...
Why do you ask?
你问这个干吗?
Anne wants a Bible!
安妮想要一本圣经
Master Cromwell can recite the whole of the New Testament.
克伦威尔大人能背诵整个新约
I think she wants to swear on it.
我觉得她是想用圣经起誓
Ah, then I probably won't do.
噢 那我可能就不能去效劳了
How did you do that?
你怎么做到的?
You.
你
Me.
我
She's in his arms.
她现在躺在他的臂弯里
Naked as she was born.
全身赤裸 像刚出生婴儿一样
She can't change her mind now.
她现在已经不能回头了
I thought they were quarrelling.
我以为他们刚刚是在吵架
They were. They like to quarrel.
的确是 他们喜欢争吵
What did she want the Bible for?
那她要圣经做什么?
To swear him. Before witnesses. He made her a binding promise.
让他在上帝的见证下起誓 他做了郑重承诺
They are married in God's sight.
他们在上帝的见证下结婚了
And he swears he'll marry her again in England and crown her queen.
他也发誓说 一回到英格兰会再举行一次婚礼 为她戴上王后冠冕
Well, well, well.
好吧 好吧 好吧
So now it's just a question of whether he can do the deed.
现在问题就是看他能不能把安妮吃掉了
For God's sake, Mary, don't frighten me.
看在上帝的份上 玛丽 别吓我
Don't worry. If he's shy, Anne will know how to help.
别担心 如果他胆怯了 安妮知道该怎么如愿
I've coached her.
我已经教过她了
Have you?
是吗?
Now what about us?
那我们现在怎么办?
It's been a long struggle to bring them together.
为了让他们俩在一起 也算是经历了漫长的斗争
I think we've earned our recreation.
我想我们已经得到消遣了
You're not still afraid of my Uncle Norfolk?
你不会还在怕我的叔叔 诺尔福克吧?
- I'm terrified of your Uncle Norfolk. - But it's not that. What is it?
-我很害怕你的那个诺尔福克叔叔          - 但这不是原因 到底因为什么?
Another?
另一个吗?
You almost murdered William Stafford.
你差点杀了威廉 斯塔福德
William, I thought you weren't coming.
威廉 我还以为你不会来了
It seems you had a reserve ready, just in case.
看来你已经有备胎了啊
You don't know what a woman's life is like!
你根本不懂一个女人的生活是怎样的！
You think you've fixed something with a man, and he doesn't turn up!
你以为你已经跟一个男人有了些感情 但他却没出现
Give you good night.
祝你晚安
No, don't go.
不 别走
I, er... I think it's time I said my prayers.
我...呃...我该去祷告了
You've been writing letters up to Chester.
你一直在信件往来切斯特
On his Majesty's business. Why?
是关于陛下的事情 为什么这么问?
I'll tell you this once, Cromwell.
我就说这一次 克伦威尔
You keep out of my family's affairs or you'll have me to deal with.
别插手我的家事 不然我就要你好看
And you'll come off worse than you can possibly imagine.
而且你根本想象不到 你会变得有多糟糕
You made a mistake threatening me, sir.
你不该恐吓我的 阁下
In the beginning was the Word and the Word was with God,
太初有道 道与神同在 道就是神
and the Word was God.
这道太初与神同在
The same was in the beginning with God.
万有是藉着他而成的
All things were made by it
凡所成的
and without it was made nothing that was made.
没有一样不是藉着他而成的
In it was life
生命在他里面
and the life was the light of men.
这生命就是人的光   [圣经 - 约翰福音]
I had to, Thomas. I couldn't live with what I'd done.
我必须这样做 托马斯 我无法再背负着我所做之事活下去了
When you're examined...
那当你被宣判的时候呢...
I'll say what I will say before my last judge -
在最终宣判前 我会说出我该说的
that the Eucharist is only bread, we have no need of penance
圣餐只不过是面包 我们没必要忏悔
and Purgatory is an invention ungrounded in scripture.
炼狱也只是圣经中所创造的无稽之谈
If some men come and tell you to go with them, I want you go with them.
如果有人来 让你跟他们走 我希望你跟他们走
They'll be my men.
那会是我派来的人
You think you can get me out of the Tower?
你觉得你能把我从伦敦塔里救出去吗?
Tyndale's Bible says "with God, nothing is impossible."
汀代尔的圣经中说"有上帝在 万物皆存有可能"
But what would be the point, Thomas?
但那又有什么意义呢 托马斯
I'd only have to walk to Paul's cross
我只需要走到保罗的十字架前
and say before the Londoners what I've already said.
在伦敦人民面前说出我想说的话
I cannot unbelieve what I believe.
我不能不相信我的信仰
Therefore, is it not the same for the male sex and the female sex?
所以 男性和女性之间确实有不相同 对吗
If on the one hand they appear different
一方面 他们在一些
with regard to some skill or other - employment?
技能或其他"职业"上 呈现出不同
Occupation.
职业
Leave us, daughter.
让我们单独聊聊 女儿
I won't have you in this devil's company.
我可不想让你跟这个恶魔呆着
I hear you can't come to the coronation
我听说你不能出席加冕礼
because you can't afford a new coat.
是因为你买不起一件新外套
Gardiner will buy you a new coat himself
伽迪纳会给你买件新外套的
- if you'll show your face on the day.  - Will he?
- 如果你那天出现的话    - 他会吗?
Indeed. I'll relish taking the ten pounds from him.
确实 能从他那儿拿走十磅都很不容易
And what will you wear?
那你要穿什么?
Oh, they're making me something, Meg.
噢 他们正给我做新衣服呢 梅格
If I avoid getting laughed at, it'll be enough.
我能不被嘲笑 就已经万幸了
I heard the Holy Maid - the Barton girl - has been to visit you.
我听说了圣女 那个姓巴顿的姑娘 来拜访过你
She has. But we wouldn't receive her.
她的确来过 但是我们不会收留她的
She has also been to visit the Lady Exeter. At her invitation.
她还受艾可赛特夫人之邀 拜访过她家
Lady Exeter is a foolish and ambitious woman.
艾可赛特夫人 不过一介愚昧不堪且又野心勃勃的妇人
Barton told her she'd be Queen of England.
巴顿告诉她 她有朝一日将会是英格兰的王后
I repeat my comment.
仍执我见
You don't believe in her visions, then?
你也不相信她的眼力吗
I don't. She does it for attention.
不相信 因为她是故意那么做的
I've written to her advising her to avoid the company
我已经写信给她 建议她少伴在位高权重的人身边
of powerful men and women and to stay at home and pray.
而是老实呆在家里祷告
As should we all. Follow your example.
我们所有人都该如此 以您为榜样
Amen. I suppose you've kept a copy?
阿门 我猜您应该保留了一份副本吧
Get it, Meg. Otherwise he might never leave.
梅格 去拿给他 否则他永远不会离开的
James Bainham.
詹姆斯 班罕
He's to be burnt.
他将被施以火刑
Ask to see Henry. He'll welcome you back like a lost child.
去求见亨利吧 他会像欢迎迷途浪子一样欢迎你归来
I'm not asking you to agree with James.
我不是让你支持詹姆斯的观点
If his doctrine is false, you can talk him back, back to Rome.
如果他的信仰有误 你可以劝他回去 回罗马去
You're an eloquent man.
你能言善辩
You're the great persuader of our age.
是我们这个时代最卓越的辩论家
But if he dies, you'll never know, will you?
但如果他驾鹤西征 你永远不会知道
Whether you could have saved his soul.
你是否能够救赎他的灵魂 对吧
You can't come in. She's in a state of undress.
你不能进去 她尚未更衣
Let him in.
让他进来吧
The King says you've never looked more beautiful.
国王陛下说您此时美过往昔
And he sends a kiss, which I told him he should deliver himself.
他让我转达一个吻 我说他还是应该亲自送达为好
What are you wearing?
你穿的这是什么？
I said no black.
我说过不要穿黑色的
It's scarlet.
这是深红色
It's a very black scarlet.
是深的发黑的红
Francis Bryan says I look like a walking bruise.
佛朗西斯 布莱恩说我看起来就像一块会行走的淤青肿块
Did you hear them cheer for me?
你听到他们为我欢呼了么
All this talk of people loving Katherine.
所有的言论都在说人们爱戴凯瑟琳
I think they just pity her.
我认为他们不过是怜悯她而已
Oh, no, they love her
噢不 他们爱戴她
because she is the daughter of two anointed sovereigns.
因为她是两位受膏的君主之女［在国王登基仪式或授予神职仪式上涂膏油于人使其神圣化 ］
They'll never love you like that Madam, any more than...
他们永远不会像爱戴凯瑟琳一样爱戴您的 至多...
Cromwell here.
就像爱戴这个克伦威尔一样而已
You may as well make your mind to it. I think...
您最好也能接受这点 我认为...
That's enough, Jane.
够了 珍妮
They say the Barton girl has prophesied
他们说巴顿小女孩已经预言了
that so-called Princess Mary will be queen.
那个所谓的玛丽公主以后会成为女王
Katherine is plotting with Exeter and Pole -
凯瑟琳正与艾可赛特以及波尔密谋
all the old Plantagenets.
她们都曾是金雀花王朝的人
- Don't distress yourself. - I'm not distressed.
- 您不要徒增烦恼  - 我不是自寻烦恼
These people want me dead.
这些人巴不得我死
But when my son is born, they'll all be powerless.
但一旦我儿子出生 他们就都无能为力了
Master Cromwell?
克伦威尔大人
I wanted to thank you.
我想要感谢您
From your present.
收到了您的礼物
Thomas Cromwell's sleeves.
托马斯 克伦威尔的袖子
How do things stand at Wolf Hall?
狼厅的事情如何了
Edward is angry, my mother is grinding her teeth.
爱德华愤怒至极 我母亲也咬牙切齿暗自生气
I would like to leave.
我想要离开
Well, if I were your father...
好吧 如果我是你父亲...
If I were to advise you, it would be to stay
如果我建议的话 建议你留下
in the service of your new queen.
效忠你们的新王后
Well, it's good to be humble. And she makes sure we are.
谦逊恭顺总是适宜的 而且她总是确保我们如此
I think she'll soften, now she has her heart's desire.
我相信她会变温和的 如今她内心已经有了渴望
This is my humble face.
我谦逊恭顺时就是这样的
Will it serve?
可以么
I think it would take you anywhere.
我觉得它让你到哪 都如鱼得水的
It came for you today.
它是今天送来的
A present from the King.
国王赏赐您的礼物
The Queen is setting off to begin her confinement.
王后准备开始闭居
We just wanted to check.
我们只是想确认一下
Are we saying "announcing the birth of a prince"
我们应该说"宣布一位王子的诞生"
or just the birth of a "child?"
还是只是说一个"孩子"的诞生
- All of our fortunes depend on this lady now
- 我们所有人的命运都系在这夫人身上了
and whether she can provide an heir,
看她能否诞下继承人了
and we all know it's a long road between a child in the womb
我们都知道一个尚在腹中的孩子 和一个已经安然躺在婴儿床里的孩子
and one safely in the crib.
不可同日而语
You look happy.
你看起来很高兴
Are you happy?
你高兴么
Yes.
开心
Because of this.
因为这孩子
I was always desired.
过去我总是想要很多
But now I'm valued, you see?
但是现在我很知足 你知道么?
And that's different.
而这孩子就是不同之处